Finding aid for the Carol Waymire collection of periodicals and ephemera LSC.2172
UCLA Library Special Collections
Carol Waymire collection of periodicals and ephemera
1910-1993
1974-1986
UCLA Library Special Collections
Waymire, Carol
LSC.2172
3.2 linear feet (7 document boxes, 1 flat box)
Carol Marie Waymire is a California based lawyer who served underrepresented communities through her work on immigration law, rights of undocumented workers, racial and sexual discrimination, workers rights on the job, and child custody for gay parents. This collection contains materials collected by Carol Waymire. It is primarily comprised of periodicals, but also includes ephemera and informational literature; these materials are all related to her lesbian, gay, feminist, and/or socialist interests and cover a wide range of cultural, economic and political spheres as well as publication location.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Provenance unknown.
This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9971974823606533
Biography/History
Carol Marie Waymire is a California-based lawyer, born in 1933 in Upper Lake, California. Coming from a poor working family, Waymire spent her childhood moving around in the rural country of Northern California before settling in Santa Rosa with her mother and siblings at the age of sixteen after her parents' divorce. She graduated from Santa Rosa High School where she was involved in sports (basketball, volleyball, the Girls Athletics Association) as well as other extramural activities and the Honor Society. Waymire was the first of her family to go to college, graduating from San Jose State University in 1956 with a major in Social Sciences and a minor in English. She taught junior high school for a number of years before travelling to Ghana for two years (1961-63) with the then newly formed Peace Corps to teach English at a government school for girls. While she later questioned the motivations and consequences of the Peace Corps' work abroad, the experience shaped the path that Waymire was to take. It led her back to school to earn a Masters in teaching English as a Second Language at UCLA (1966), after which she taught ESL for more than ten years in Los Angeles at the Evans Adult School.
Her experience teaching non-English speaking adults, largely people from Asia and Latin America who faced poverty and racial and class discrimination yet had no resources or recourse to legal support, is what drew Waymire to pursue law. These experiences and her own struggles supporting an aging grandmother, who had a stroke and little medical support, turned Waymire towards socialism as an answer to the over-arching problems she identified in the capitalist system that had failed her family and her students. Waymire received her law degree from The People's College of Law (1977- 1981), a private, non-profit law school in downtown Los Angeles which offers a part-time, four-year evening Juris Doctor program aimed at progressive social change and social justice. As a lawyer, Waymire was interested in immigration law, rights of undocumented workers, racial and sexual discrimination, workers rights on the job, and child custody for gay parents.
As a socialist feminist, Waymire was active in the lesbian, gay and feminist activism in Los Angeles, and California more broadly. As evidenced in this collection, she was involved in the organizations and causes such as the LA Women's Forum, Lesbian Feminists of LA, and the movement against Proposition 6 in 1978. More generally, she was active on issues such as gay rights, violence against women, and abortion.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials collected by Carol Waymire. It is primarily comprised of periodicals, but also includes ephemera and informational literature; these materials are all related to her lesbian, gay, feminist, and/or socialist interests. The periodicals, which make up the bulk of the collection, cover a wide range of cultural, political and economic interests related to gay rights and women's rights issues. These include LA-based publications as well as those from California and the rest of the country.
This collection also includes a number of materials from organizations and events in which Waymire was involved or interested, such as flyers, programs, mailings, and informational pamphlets. It also includes informational literature on women's health, socialist feminism, and socialism, as well as a few meeting minutes and notes from organizational meetings in which Waymire was involved, like the LA Women's Forum.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Periodicals, 1974-1993
Series 2: Personal Papers and Ephemera, 1910-1985
Related Online Items Available
Portions of the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives Subject Files have been digitized and are available online: June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives Subject Files (863 items)
- Periodicals, 1974-1993; 1974-1986
  Scope and Content
  This series contains sets of a number of periodicals collected by Carol Waymire. These periodicals cover a range of interests; lesbian art and culture, feminist and socialist activism, anti-violence women's rights, gay' rights and a range of economic and political concerns. The periodicals included are from Los Angeles as well as various other parts of California and the country, particularly the mid west. The most well represented periodicals include Chrysalis, a national magazine of women's culture published in LA and The Lesbian Tide, a feminist lesbian publication. Publications from the West Coast include Lesbian Voices (San Jose), Radical Women Publications (Seattle), and Sister (San Francisco). Publications from the Midwest include Lavender Women (Chicago), The Lesbian Insider (Minneapolis), and Lesbian Connection (E Lansing, MI). Periodicals such as Come Out Fighting: The Newspaper of the Lavender and Red Union, Women Against Violence Against Women's Newsletter, LA Women's Union Newspaper and The Lesbian Insider illustrate Waymire's activist interests. The series also contains single issues of a number of publications related to lesbian, feminist and socialist activities. Taken as a whole, this series not only provides a view of the personal interests of the collection's creator, Carol Waymire, but insight into a world of politically active and radical feminism and gay rights interests in the late 70's and early 80's that bridges the gap between social, cultural and political spheres.
  Organization and Arrangement
  The series is organized alphabetically by title of publication. Single issue publications are grouped together.
  - A-B, 1975-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chrysalis, a Magazine of Women's Culture: Los Angeles, CA: No. 1-3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chrysalis, a Magazine of Women's Culture: Los Angeles, CA: No. 4-6, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chrysalis, a Magazine of Women's Culture: Los Angeles, CA: No. 7,9, 10, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Come Out Fighting - The Newspaper of the Lavender and Red Union: Los Angeles, CA: No. 6,12-21, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Coyote Howls - The Intermittent Journal of Coyote, the Loose Women's Organization: San Francisco, CA: Vol. 3-6, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - D-F, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - G-H, 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gay Community News: Boston, MA (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - L, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - L.A. Women's Union Newsletter: Los Angeles, CA, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lavender Women: Chicago's Lesbian/Feminist Newspaper: Chicago, IL: Vol. 4 No. 2-5, Vol. 5 No. 1, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Lesbian Insider: Minneapolis, MN: No. 1-8, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lesbian Connection: East Lansing, MI: Vol. 2 No. 5, Vol. 3 No. 6,8, Vol. 15 No. 4, 1976-1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Lesbian News: Los Angeles, CA: No. 13, 26, 37-42, Vol. 5 No. 4-8, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Lesbian Tide: Los Angeles, CA: Vol. 4 No. 5,8, Vol. 5 No. 2-6, Vol. 6 1-6, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Lesbian Tide: Los Angeles, CA: Vol. 7 No. 1-6, Vol. 8 No. 1-3, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Lesbian Tide: Los Angeles, CA: Vol. 8 No. 4-6, Vol. 9 No. 1-6, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lesbian Voices: San Jose, CA: Vol. 1 No. 3,4, Vol. 2 No. 1,3, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Life Magazine Special Report, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - M-N, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - R-S, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Radical Women Publications: Seattle, WA, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Second Wave - A Magazine for the New Feminism: Cambridge, MA: Vol. 4 No. 1-4, Vol. 5 No. 1-4, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sister, West Coast Feminist Newspaper: Los Angeles CA: Vol. 4 No. 5, Vol. 6 No. 8,9, Vol.7 No. 1,2, Vol. 8 No. 2, Vol. 10 No. 1-3, 1973-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - W, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Women Against Violence Against Women - Newsletter: Los Angeles, CA: No. 2-7, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - A Woman's Journey: Columbia, MA, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Y-Z, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Magazine Covers, 1991-1997 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Personal Papers and Ephemera, 1910-1985; 1975-1985
  The series includes some of Waymire's personal papers, such as her application to Law School and her Torts exams. The bulk of the series is comprised of mailings, flyers, publicity material, pamphlets, event programs and informational literature from a number of organizations and causes in which Waymire was involved. Organizations and events represented include the Christopher Street West Gay Parade and other gay pride festivals, Women on Wheels, The LA Community Women's Chorus annual shows, and The Lesbian Writers Forum. There are also some directories and contact lists of various women-focused networks.
  Materials from organizations like The LA Women's Forum, Lesbian Feminists if Los Angeles and WAVAW (Women against Violence against Women) which focus on rape, abortion and violence against women provide insight into Waymire's activist interests. There is a set of materials devoted to mobilizing against Proposition 6, known as the Briggs Initiative, which specifically targeted gay parents and their rights. Lastly, there is a significant focus on socialist feminism, particularly regarding economic and political concerns; these materials include informational pamphlets, statistical and census reports on women and poverty and some administrative records from the United Workers Union and The New American Movement.
  This series is organized alphabetically. Personal papers are found at the beginning of the series.
  - Personal Papers: Address Book, Year Book, etc, 1950-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Personal Papers: Law School Application, Torts Exams, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Personal Papers: The Winters Family History, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Directories and Contacts: Women's Networks, 1977-1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Events, Flyers and Programs (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Event Posters, 1992-1995 (Box 8)
  - LA Women's Forum (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lesbian Feminists of Los Angeles, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Literature, Outreach and Events: Gay Rights, Activism, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Literature, Outreach and Events: Gay Rights, Anti-violence, Feminist Music, Dance and Film, 1975-1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Literature, Outreach and Events: Rape, Abortion, Other Issues, 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - No on Proposition 6: The Briggs Initiative, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - No on Proposition 6: The Briggs Initiative, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets and Informational Literature, 1972-1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Press Clippings (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Promotional Buttons and Pins (Box 8)
  - Socialist Feminism: Organizational, Informational Literature, 1974-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Feminism: Organizational, Informational Literature, 1974-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Department of Commerce, Census: "Characteristics of Population Below Poverty Level:1977" (Box 7, Folder 3)